part 2 chapter 2.
Winston picked his way up the lane through dappled light and shade, stepping
out into pools of gold wherever the Bowers parted.
Under the trees to the left of him the ground was misty with bluebells. The air
seemed to kiss one's skin. It was the 2nd of May. From somewhere deeper in the
heart of the wood came the droning of ring dubs
He was a bit early. There had been no difficulties about the journey, and the
girl was so evidently experienced that he was less frightened than he would normally have been.
Presumably she could be trusted to find a safe place.
In general you could not assume that you were much safer in the country than in London.
There were no telescreens, of course, but there was always the danger of concealed
microphones by which your voice might be picked up and recognized
besides, it was not easy to make a journey by yourself without attracting attention.
For distances of less than 100 kilometers it was not necessary to get
your passport endorsed, but sometimes there were patrols hanging about the
railway stations, who examined the papers of any Party member they found there and
asked awkward questions.
However, no patrols had appeared, and on the walk from the station he had made
sure by cautious backward glances that he was not being followed.
The train was full of pearls in holiday mood because of the summary weather.
The wooden seated carriage in which he traveled was filled to overflowing by a
single enormous family, ranging from a toothless great-grandmother to a month
old baby, going out to spend an afternoon with 'in-laws' in the country, and, as they
freely explained to Winston, to get hold of a little black market butter.
The lane widened, and in a minute he came to the footpath she had told him of, a
mere cattle track which plunged between the bushes.
He had no watch, but it could not be 15 yet.
The blue belts were so thick underfoot that it was impossible not to tread on
them. He knelt down and began picking some, partly to pass the time away, but
also from a vague idea that he would like to have a bunch of flowers to offer
the girl when they met. He had got together a big bunch and was smelling
their faint sickly scent when a sound at his back froze him, the unmistakable
crackle of a foot on twigs.
He went on picking bluebells. It was the best thing to do. It might be the girl, or
he might have been followed after all. To look around was to show guilt. He picked
another and another hand fell lightly on his shoulder.
He looked up.
It was the girl.
She shook her head, evidently as a warning that he must keep silent, then,
parted the bushes and quickly led the way along the narrow track into the wood.
Obviously she had been that way before, for she dodged to the boggy bits as though by habit.
Winston followed, still clasping his bunch of flowers. His first feeling was
relief, but as he watched the strong slender body moving in front of him, with
the scarlet sash that was just tight enough to bring out the curve of her
hips, the sense of his own inferiority was heavy upon him.
Even now it seems quite likely that when she turned around and looked at him she
would draw back after all.
The sweetness of the air and the greenness of the leaves daunted him.
Already on the walk from the station the May sunshine had made him feel dirty and
eatilated the creature of indoors, with the dust of London in the pores of his skin.
It occurred to him that till now she had probably never seen him in broad
daylight in the open.
They came to the fallen tree that she had spoken of.
The girl hopped over and forced apart the bushes, in which there did not seem
to be an opening. When Winston followed her, he found that they were in a natural
clearing, a tiny grassy knoll surrounded by tall saplings that shuttered in completely.
The girl stopped and turned.
'Here we are,' she said.
He was facing her at several paces' distance.
As yet he did not dare move nearer to her.
'I didn't want to say anything in the lane,' she went on, 'in case there's a mic
hidden there.
I don't suppose there is, but there could be.
There's always the chance of one of those swine recognizing your voice. We're all right here.'
He still had not the courage to approach her.
'We're all right here?' he repeated stupidly.
'Yes. Look at the trees there were small ashes, which at some
time had been cut down and had sprouted up again into a forest of poles, none of
them thicker than one's wrist.
'There's nothing big enough to hide a mic in. Besides, I've been here before.'
They were only making conversation. He had managed to move closer to her now.
She stood before him very upright, with a smile on her face that looked faintly
ironical, as though she were wondering why he was so slow to act.
The blue bells had cascaded onto the ground.
They seemed to have fallen of their own accord.
He took her hand.
'Would you believe,' he said, 'that till this moment I didn't know what color your eyes were
there were brown, he noted, a rather light shade of brown, with dark lashes.
'Now that you've seen what I'm really like, can you still bear to look at me?'
'Yes, easily.'
'I'm 39 years old. I've got a wife that I can't get rid of. I've got varicose veins.
I've got five false teeth.'
'I couldn't care less,' said the girl.
The next moment, it was hard to say by whozak she was in his arms. At the
beginning he had no feeling except sheer incredulity.
The youthful body was strained against his own, the mass of dark hair was
against his face, and yes! actually she had turned her face up and he was
kissing the wide red mouth.
She had clasped her arms about his neck, she was calling him darling, precious one, loved one.
He had pulled her down onto the ground, she was utterly unresisting, he could do
what he liked with her.
But the truth was that he had no physical sensation, except that of mere contact.
All he felt was incredulity and pride. He was glad that this was happening, but he
had no physical desire.
It was too soon, her youth and prettiness had frightened him, he was too much used
to living without women— —he did not know the reason.
The girl picked herself up and pulled a Blue Bell out of her hair.
She sat against him, putting her arm around his waist.
'Never mind, dear. There's no hurry. We've got the whole afternoon. Isn't this a
splendid Hideout I found it when I got lost once on a community hike. If anyone
was coming you could hear them a hundred meters away.'
'What is your name?' said Winston.
'Julia.
I know yours.
It's Winston— —Winston Smith.'
'How did you find that out?'
'I expect I'm better at finding things out than you are, dear.
Tell me, what did you think of me before that day I gave you the note?'
He did not feel any temptation to tell lies to her. It was even a sort of Love
offering to start off by telling the worst.
'I hated the sight of you,' he said. 'I wanted to rape you and then murder you afterwards.
Two weeks ago I thought seriously of smashing your head in with a cobblestone.
If you really want to know, I imagined that you had something to do with the Thought Police.'
The girl laughed delightedly, evidently taking this as a tribute to the
excellence of her disguise.
'Not the Thought Police! You didn't honestly think that?'
'Well, perhaps not exactly that. But from your general appearance—
—merely because you're young and fresh and healthy, you understand— —I thought that probably———'
'You thought I was a good Party member.
Pure in word and deed.
Banners, processions, slogans, games, community hikes— —all that stuff.
And you thought that if I had a quarter of a chance I'd denounce you as a
thought criminal and get you killed off?'
'Yes, something of that kind. A great many young girls are like that, you know.'
'It's this bloody thing that does it,' she said, ripping off the scarlet sash of the
Junior Anti-Sex League and flinging it onto a bow Then, as though touching her waist had
reminded her of something, she felt in the pocket of her overalls and produced
a small slab of chocolate.
She broke it in half and gave one of the pieces to Winston.
Even before he had taken it he knew by the smell that it was very unusual chocolate.
It was dark and shiny, and was wrapped in silver paper.
Chocolate normally was dull Brown crumbly stuff that tasted, as nearly as
one could describe it, like the smoke of a rubbish fire.
But at some time or another he had tasted chocolate like the piece she had given him.
The first whiff of its scent had stirred up some memory which he could not pin
down, but which was powerful and troubling.
'Where did you get this stuff?' he said.
'Black market,' she said indifferently.
'Actually I am that sort of girl, to look at.
I'm good at games. I was a troop leader in the Spies. I do voluntary work three
evenings a week for the Junior anti-sex League.
Hours and hours I've spent pasting their bloody rot all over London. I always
carry one end of a banner in the processions. I always look cheerful and I
never shirk anything. Always yell with the crowd, that's what I say.
It's the only way to be safe.'
The first fragment of chocolate had melted on Winston's tongue. The taste was
delightful. But there was still that memory moving around the edges of his
consciousness, something strongly felt but not reducible to definite shape, like
an object seen out of the corner of one's eye.
He pushed it away from him, aware only that it was the memory of some action
which he would have liked to undo but could not.
'You are very young,' he said. 'You were 10 or 15 years younger than I am.
What could you see to attract you in a man like me?'
'It was something in your face. I thought I'd take a chance. I'm good at spotting
people who don't belong. As soon as I saw you I knew you were against Them,
it appeared, meant the Party, and above all the Inner Party, about whom she
talked with an open jeering hatred which made Winston feel uneasy, although he
knew that they were safe here if they could be safe anywhere.
A thing that astonished him about her was the coarseness of her language.
Party members were supposed not to swear, and Winston himself very seldom did
swear, aloud, at any rate.
Julia, however, seemed unable to mention the Party, and especially the Inner Party,
without using the kind of words that you saw chalked up in dripping alleyways. He
did not dislike it. It was merely one symptom of her revolt against the Party
in all its ways, and somehow it seemed natural and healthy, like the sneeze of a
horse that smells bad hay.
They had left the clearing and were wandering again through the checkered
shade, with their arms around each other's waists whenever it was wide
enough to walk to a breast He noticed how much softer her waist
seemed to feel now that the sash was gone.
They did not speak above a whisper.
Outside the clearing, Julia said, it was better to go quietly.
Presently they had reached the edge of the little wood. She stopped him.
'Don't go out into the open. There might be someone watching. We're all right if
we keep behind the bows They were standing in the shade of hazel
bushes. The sunlight, filtering through innumerable leaves, was still hot on their faces.
Winston looked out into the field beyond, and underwent a curious, slow shock of recognition.
He knew it by sight. An old, close-bitten pasture, with a footpath wandering across
it and a mold Hill here and there.
In the ragged hedge on the opposite side the bowels of the elm trees swayed just
perceptibly in the breeze, and their leaves stirred faintly in dense masses like women's hair.
Surely somewhere nearby, but out of sight, there must be a stream with green pools
where days were swimming?
'Isn't there a stream somewhere near here?'
he whispered.
'That's right, there is a stream. It's at the edge of the next field, actually
they're efficient great big ones. You can watch them lying in the pools under the
willow trees, waving their tails.'
'It's the Golden Country— —almost,' he murmured.
'The Golden Country?'
'It's nothing, really. A landscape I've seen sometimes in a dream.'
'Look!' whispered Julia.
A thrusher delighted on a bow not five meters away, almost at the level of their
faces. Perhaps it had not seen them.
It was in the sun, they in the shade.
It spread out its wings, fitted them carefully into place again, ducked its
head for a moment, as though making a sort of obeisance to the sun, and then
began to pour forth a torrent of song.
In the afternoon hush the volume of sound was startling.
Winston and Julia clung together, fascinated.
The music went on and on, minute after minute, with astonishing variations, never
once repeating itself, almost as if the bird were deliberately showing off its virtuosity.
Sometimes it stopped for a few seconds, spread out and resettled its wings, then
swelled its speckled breast and again burst into song.
Winston watched it with a sort of vague reverence.
For whom, for what, was that bird singing?
No mate, no rival was watching it. What made it sit at the edge of the lonely
wood and pour its music into nothingness?
He wondered whether after all there was a microphone hidden somewhere near.
He and Julia had spoken only in low whispers, and it would not pick up what
they had said, but it would pick up the thrush.
Perhaps at the other end of the instrument some small, beetle-like man was listening intently—
—listening to that by degrees the flood of music drove all
speculations out of his mind. It was as though it were a kind of liquid stuff
that poured all over him and got mixed up with the sunlight that filtered through the leaves.
He stopped thinking and merely felt.
The girl's waist in the bend of his arm was soft and warm.
He pulled her around so that they were breast to breast; her body seemed to melt into his.
Wherever his hands moved it was all his yielding as water.
Their mouths clung together; it was quite different from the hard kisses they had
exchanged earlier.
When they moved their faces apart again both of them sighed deeply.
The birds took fright and fled with a clatter of wings.
Winston put his lips against her ear.
'Now, he whispered.
'Not here,' she whispered back. 'Come back to the Hideout It's safer.'
Quickly, with an occasional crackle of twigs, they threaded their way back to
the clearing. When they were once inside the ring of saplings she turned and faced him.
They were both breathing fast, but the smile had reappeared round the corners of her mouth.
She stood looking at him for an instant, then felt at the zipper of her overalls.
And, yes! it was almost as in his dream.
Almost as swiftly as he had imagined it, she had torn her clothes off, and when
she flung them aside it was with that same magnificent gesture by which a
whole civilization seemed to be annihilated.
Her body gleamed white in the sun. But for a moment he did not look at her body;
his eyes were anchored by the freckled face with its faint, bold smile.
He knelt down before her and took her hands in his.
'Have you done this before?'
'Of course. Hundreds of times— —well, scores of times, anyway.'
'With Party members?' 'Yes, always with Party members.'
'With members of the Inner Party?'
'Not with those why no. But there's plenty that would if they got half a chance.
They're not so holy as they make out.'
His heart leapt.
Scores of times she had done it: he wished it had been hundreds— —thousands.
Anything that hinted at corruption always filled him with a wild hope.
Who knew, perhaps the Party was rotten under the surface, its cult of
strenuousness and self-denial simply a sham concealing iniquity.
If he could have infected the whole lot of them with leprosy or syphilis, how
gladly he would have done so!
Anything to rot, to weaken, to undermine!
He pulled her down so that they were kneeling face to face.
'Listen. The more men you've had, the more I love you. Do you understand that?'
'Yes, perfectly.'
'I hate purity, I hate goodness! I don't want any virtue to exist anywhere. I want
everyone to be corrupt to the bones.'
'Well then, I ought to suit you, dear. I'm corrupt to the bones.'
'You like doing this? I don't mean simply me: I mean the thing in itself?'
'I adore it.'
That was above all what he wanted to hear.
Not merely the love of one person, but the animal instinct, the simple undifferentiated desire:
that was the force that would tear the Party to pieces. He pressed her down upon
the grass, among the fallen bluebells.
This time there was no difficulty.
Presently the rising and falling of their breasts slowed to normal speed, and
in a sort of pleasant helplessness they fell apart.
The sun seemed to have grown hotter. They were both sleepy.
He reached out for the discarded overalls and pulled them partly over her.
Almost immediately they fell asleep and slept for about half an hour.
Winston worked first. He sat up and watched the freckled face, still
peacefully asleep, pillowed on the palm of her hand.
Except for her mouth, you could not call her beautiful.
There was a line or two around the eyes, if you looked closely. The short dark
hair was extraordinarily thick and soft.
It occurred to him that he still did not know her surname or where she lived.
The young, strong body, now helpless in sleep awoken him a pitying, protecting feeling.
But the mindless tenderness that he had felt under the hazel tree, while the
thrush was singing, had not quite come back.
He pulled the overalls aside and studied her smooth white flank.
In the old days, he thought, a man looked at a girl's body and saw that it was
desirable, and that was the end of the story.
But you could not have pure love or pure lust nowadays. No emotion was pure,
because everything was mixed up with fear and hatred.
Their embrace had been a battle, the climax of victory.
It was a blow struck against the Party.
It was a political act